New York State Coalition for Criminal Justice; Records apap012
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
- Coalition Administration Files, 1975-1984; 1; 5.33 cubic ft.
  - Satellites - Elmira Network, 1975-1979 (Box 15 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 4)
  - Satellites - Mid-Hudson Network, 1975-1979 (Box 15 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 5)
  - Satellites - Nassau Network, 1975-1981 (Box 15 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 6)
  - Satellites - New York City Network, 1975-1980 (Box 15 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 7)
  - Satellites - North Country Network, 1975-1978 (Box 15 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 8)
  - Satellites - Plattsburgh Network Potential, 1978 (Box 15 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 9)
  - Satellites - Rapid Communications Network: Guidelines & Workshops, 1977-1980 (Box 15 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 10)
  - Satellites - Miscellaneous papers, 1975-1977 (Box 16 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 1)
  - Satellites - Monitograms, 1977-1980 (Box 16 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 2)
  - Satellites - Rochester Network, 1975-1980 (Box 16 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 3)
  - Satellites - Suffolk Network, 1976-1981 (Box 16 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 4)
  - Satellites - Syracuse Network, 1975-1981 (Box 16 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 5)
  - Satellites - Westchester Network, 1975-1981 (Box 16 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 6)
  - Senate Democratic Task Force On Criminal Justice, 1982 (Box 16 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 7)
  - Sentencing Improvement Act, 1982 (Box 16 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 8)
  - S.T.O.P., Stop The Olympic Prison, 1978-1979 (Box 16 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 9)
  - Suffolk County Conference On Juvenile And Criminal Justice, Inc., 1978-1983 (Box 16 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 10)
  - Urban Information Interpreters, Inc., 1983 (Box 16 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 11)
  - Vietnam And Criminal Justice, 1982 (Box 16 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 12)
  - Volunteer Attorney Service Team, 1982-1983 (Box 16 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 13)
  - Volunteer Center Of Albany, 1982-1983 (Box 16 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 14)
  - Westchester Alliance, 1978-1981 (Box 16 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 15)
- Coalition Meetings File, 1975-1983; 2; 0.67 cubic ft.
  Contains the records of the Coalition's annual meetings, and special meetings on topics of interest to criminal justice reformers organized by the Coalition. The series also contains statements of goals and purpose, minutes, agendas, by-laws, proposed amendments to the by-laws, strategy suggestions, and several questionnaires directed for committee members. Also included are lists of organizations by caucuses in geographic regions, lists of the individuals in the different caucuses, and attendance at meetings. Notes of the executive and policy committee are available, they mainly include discussion of sub-committees work, and confirming new policies. The file also contains information on the Coalition's 1979 SuperSession, a two day agenda devoted to a discussion of topics such as good time, temporary release, and the death penalty. Super Sessions were also held in 1980 and 1981, where the main topics were inappropriate confinement and community corrections. Series also contains cassette tapes of panel questions from March 22-23, 1982, "Managing the Crisis: Population Policy".
  - Annual Meetings, 1975-1979 (Box 1 (2-Coalition Meetings File), Folder 1)
  - Annual Meeting, 1979 October 4 (Box 1 (2-Coalition Meetings File), Folder 2)
  - Annual Meeting, 1980 October 9 (Box 1 (2-Coalition Meetings File), Folder 3)
  - Annual Meeting, 1981 October 10 (Box 1 (2-Coalition Meetings File), Folder 4)
  - Annual Conference, 1982 (Box 1 (2-Coalition Meetings File), Folder 5)
  - Annual Conference, 1982 October 23 (Box 1 (2-Coalition Meetings File), Folder 6)
  - Caucuses, 1982 (Box 1 (2-Coalition Meetings File), Folder 7)
  - "Ending Unnecessary Imprisonment" Conference, 1980 (Box 2 (2-Coalition Meetings File), Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee & Policy Committee Meeting, 1975-1978 (Box 2 (2-Coalition Meetings File), Folder 2)
  - "Gathering of the Criminal Justice Gang" Backman Summit, 1979 August (Box 2 (2-Coalition Meetings File), Folder 3)
  - "Managing the Crisis: Population and Policy", 1982 March 3-22; cassette tapes (Box 2 (2-Coalition Meetings File), Folder 4)
  - Super Session, 1979 (Box 2 (2-Coalition Meetings File), Folder 5)
  - "Inappropriate Confinement", 1980 (Box 2 (2-Coalition Meetings File), Folder 6)
  - Super Session - Community Corrections, 1981 (Box 2 (2-Coalition Meetings File), Folder 7)
  - Super Session - Community Corrections, 1981 (Box 2 (2-Coalition Meetings File), Folder 8)
- Funding Files, 1976-1982; 3; 0.67 cubic ft.
  Included is a financial report for the fiscal year 1977-1979, and a proposal for training the Coalition's satellites to become more effective 1979. Known funding agents include the Albany Focus Churches Task Force, the Albany Rotary Club. Community service society, New York State Catholic Conference, United Methodist Women, the Judicial Process Commission, United Presbyterian Women, and by far the greatest funding support was received from the New York State Council of Churches. Membership dues was also added to funding. Also found is a 1976 grant proposal by the coalition for an education program in criminal justice for citizens, elected officials, and administrators, a 1977 supplement is also included. Also present are Funding requirement updates 1978-1979 and a progress report to the New York State Council of Churches. Grant request/proposal samples from the coalition to several possible funding organizations, donations and paid membership dues listings for 1981-1982 can also be found.
  - Albany Catholic Diocese, 1979-1981 (Box 1 (3-Funding Files), Folder 1)
  - Albany Focus Churches (Task Force), 1982 (Box 1 (3-Funding Files), Folder 2)
  - Albany Rotary Club, 1980 (Box 1 (3-Funding Files), Folder 3)
  - Burden Foundation, 1979 (Box 1 (3-Funding Files), Folder 4)
  - Capital District Foundation, 1981 (Box 1 (3-Funding Files), Folder 5)
  - Christians United In Mission, 1977-1981 (Box 1 (3-Funding Files), Folder 6)
  - Coalition funding proposal, 1976-1980 (Box 1 (3-Funding Files), Folder 7)
  - Community Service Society, 1980 (Box 1 (3-Funding Files), Folder 8)
  - Composite foundation & proposal information, 1978-1979 (Box 1 (3-Funding Files), Folder 9)
  - Corporate Sponsorship Plan, Undated (Box 1 (3-Funding Files), Folder 10)
  - Dewar Foundation; St. James Episcopal Church, 1980 (Box 1 (3-Funding Files), Folder 11)
  - Donations & dues listing, 1981-1982 (Box 1 (3-Funding Files), Folder 12)
  - Edna McConnel Clark Foundation, 1979 (Box 2 (3-Funding Files), Folder 1)
  - Episcopal foundation annual reports (public interest, public relations)1976-79 Haas Memorial Haas Memorial Foundation - Watertown, 1980-1981 (Box 2 (3-Funding Files), Folder 2)
  - Knudsen Funding - Service Exploration, 1977-1978 (Box 2 (3-Funding Files), Folder 3)
  - McDonald Foundation, 1980 (Box 2 (3-Funding Files), Folder 4)
  - Methodist, 1978-1979 (Box 2 (3-Funding Files), Folder 5)
  - National Council on Crime Delinquency Coalition/Clark, 1977-1978 (Box 2 (3-Funding Files), Folder 6)
  - New York State Catholic Conference, 1979-1982 (Box 2 (3-Funding Files), Folder 7)
  - New York Yearly Meeting Prisons Committee, 1980-1983 (Box 2 (3-Funding Files), Folder 8)
  - Presbyterian - Presbytery of Albany, 1979-1982 (Box 2 (3-Funding Files), Folder 9)
  - Presbyterian, 1978 (Box 2 (3-Funding Files), Folder 10)
  - Women's Opportunity Giving, 1977-1978 (Box 2 (3-Funding Files), Folder 11)
  - Proposal materials, 1977-1980 (Box 2 (3-Funding Files), Folder 12)
  - Resource proposal sample, 1976-1977 (Box 2 (3-Funding Files), Folder 13)
  - Proposal materials/Satellite Training Conference, 1979 (Box 2 (3-Funding Files), Folder 14)
  - Sample funding letter, 1978 (Box 2 (3-Funding Files), Folder 15)
  - Thorn fund, 1980 (Box 2 (3-Funding Files), Folder 16)
  - Re: Work-study student, 1981 (Box 2 (3-Funding Files), Folder 17)
- New York State Commission of Corrections, 1975-1983; 4; 1.0 cubic ft.
  The file consists of documents received by the Coalition from the New York State Commission On Corrections. Founded in 1895, the commission is charged in its legislative mandate with general oversight responsibilities for the jails, prisons, and lockups located in New York State. The series includes information on the commission, its purpose, goals, and officials. Many reports are included starting with Commissioner Coughlin's report to the Correctional Association of N.Y. 1982 in which he characterizes the association's report as irresponsible; the final report of the special Attica investigation 1975; the Judicial Process Commission report on Attica 1976; and the State Commission of Correction staff report concerning the abuse of authority at the Attica correctional facility 1977. The series also includes audit reports on rehabilitation programs for 1973/78, restitution reports and a comparative study of cost of service delivery between N.Y., California, Michigan, Pennsylvania, and Texas. Other Commission on Corrections' reports include those on the overcrowding of jails 1980/82; on prison alternatives 1981/82; and on prison health maintenance 1979/80. Guidelines for minimum standards and regulations for management of county jails and penitentiaries can also be found in the collection. These standards concern visitations, correspondence, security and supervision, hygiene, medical, access to media, legal services, physical restraint, maximum prisoner capacity, fire safety, staffing requirements, overcrowding, lock ins, recreation, religion, access to courts, telephone calls, and packages.
  - Appointment of Correctional Officials, 1975-1979 (Box 1 (4-New York State Commission of Corrections), Folder 1)
  - Article 3: Correction Law, 1975; 1980 (Box 1 (4-New York State Commission of Corrections), Folder 2)
  - Attica investigations, 1975-1977 (Box 1 (4-New York State Commission of Corrections), Folder 3)
  - Audit reports - Selected Operating Practices, 1974; 1977 (Box 1 (4-New York State Commission of Corrections), Folder 4)
  - Commission and Corrections Committee, 1979-1980 (Box 1 (4-New York State Commission of Corrections), Folder 5)
  - Correctional Restitution, 1976; 1980; 1983 (Box 1 (4-New York State Commission of Corrections), Folder 6)
  - Management Productivity, 1977; 1979-1981 (Box 1 (4-New York State Commission of Corrections), Folder 7)
  - Minimum Standards & Regulations (folder 1), 1975-1976 (Box 2 (4-New York State Commission of Corrections), Folder 1)
  - Minimum Standards & Regulations (folder 2), 1977-1980 (Box 2 (4-New York State Commission of Corrections), Folder 2)
  - Jail Statistics, 1977-1979 (Box 2 (4-New York State Commission of Corrections), Folder 3)
  - New York State Assoc. Of Counties, 1978-1983 (Box 2 (4-New York State Commission of Corrections), Folder 4)
  - Prison Health Maintenance, 1978-1981 (Box 2 (4-New York State Commission of Corrections), Folder 5)
  - Proposals on Alternatives, 1975-1980 (Box 2 (4-New York State Commission of Corrections), Folder 6)
  - Public Hearings on Problems of Prison System, 1975-1981 (Box 3 (4-New York State Commission of Corrections), Folder 1)
  - Second Felony Offenders, 1960-1970; 1973-1974 (Box 3 (4-New York State Commission of Corrections), Folder 2)
  - Sheriff's reports, Undated (Box 3 (4-New York State Commission of Corrections), Folder 3)
  - Albany - Greene County Reports, 1977-1979 (Box 3 (4-New York State Commission of Corrections), Folder 4)
  - Herkimer - Rensselaer County, 1977 (Box 3 (4-New York State Commission of Corrections), Folder 5)
  - Rockland - Yates County, 1979 (Box 3 (4-New York State Commission of Corrections), Folder 6)
  - Temporary Release Programs, 1976-1978 (Box 3 (4-New York State Commission of Corrections), Folder 7)
- Correctional Facilities File, 1975-1981; 5; 0.67 cubic ft.
  Included is correspondence between the Coalition and prisoners. Prisoner correspondence concerns membership information, coalition updates, access to legal bills, references to other organizations, and asking of employment agencies able to help them after their time is served. The series also contains official prison descriptions of the facilities and its activities. Access to this series is restricted.
  - Albion, 1978-1979 (Box 1 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 1)
  - Arthur Kill, 1979 (Box 1 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 2)
  - Attica, 1978-1980 (Box 1 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 3)
  - Auburn, 1977-1980 (Box 1 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 4)
  - Bedford Hills, 1976-1980 (Box 1 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 5)
  - Camp Adirondack, 1979; 1980 (Box 1 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 6)
  - Camp McGregor, 1980-1981 (Box 1 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 7)
  - Camp Pharsalia, 1978; 1980 (Box 1 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 8)
  - Clinton, 1978-1980 (Box 1 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 9)
  - Coxsackie, 1978 (Box 1 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 10)
  - Downstate, 1979; 1981 (Box 1 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 11)
  - Eastern, 1978-1980 (Box 1 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 12)
  - Elmira, 1978-1979 (Box 1 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 13)
  - Fishkill, 1978-1979 (Box 2 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 1)
  - Great Meadows, 1978-1980 (Box 2 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 2)
  - Green Haven, 1978-1980 (Box 2 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 3)
  - Hudson, 1976; 1980 (Box 2 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 4)
  - Mid-Orange, 1976-1979 (Box 2 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 5)
  - Mt. McGregor, 1979 (Box 2 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 6)
  - Ossining, 1975; 1978-1980 (Box 2 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 7)
  - Otisville, 1976; 1980 (Box 2 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 8)
  - Queensboro, 1976-1979 (Box 2 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 9)
  - Taconic, 1978 (Box 2 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 10)
  - Wall Kill, 1980 (Box 2 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 11)
  - Woodburne, 1978-1979 (Box 2 (5-Correctional Facilities File), Folder 12)
- Division of Parole File, 1973-1983; 6; 0.33 cubic ft.
  The file consists primarily of correspondence and reports received from the Division of Parole. Included is the National Survey of Good-Time Laws And Administrative Procedures for 1973, which was distributed by the Research and Development Division of the Texas Department of Corrections, along with Uniform Parole reports summary tables from 1974 for male prisoners. A list of the 1975 New York State Parole Board members can be found, including salaries and term expirations. In addition, tables of probation information for 1974 are included. Also found is the forty-seventh annual report of the Board of Parole of the Department of Correctional Services for the year of 1976, this report includes such topics as rules and regulations, types of sentences, methods/basis of release, violation of parole and hearings. In addition a report from the Task Force on Criminal Sentencing which discusses fair and certain punishment is available for 1976.
  In Albany on October of 1977 a hearing was held on the subject of standards and goals of the criminal justice system, in which many organizations testified. These reports are included and are as follows, the Delphi Report 1977, a report from the Town of Horseheads Youth Bureau addressing Juvenile Justice standards and Goals 1977, a "Philosophy of Sanctions" paper written by the New York State Standards for Sentencing in 1977, testimony given by the New York State Council of Churches and a report of the presentation made by the Metropolitan Police and the Nassau County at the hearing. A general commentary of the role of the parole board is also included. A preliminary draft of the standards and goals are included. Other reports that can be found are the New York State Department of Correctional Services temporary release program discussing rules and regulations 1977, and the New York State Division of Parole Annual Statistical Report for 1977,1978 and a revised guidelines application manual for 1979. A report on an overview of options in reducing prison crowding for 1981 is included, a New York State Division of youth policy and procedures manual 1982, a New York State Parole handbook 1980, and correspondence between Peter Pollack and those who helped him with the development of the good time reform project 1981-1982. Finally a computerized code listing of parole denials for 1980 can be found.
  - Division of Parole, 1973-1976 (Box 1 (6-Division of Parole File), Folder 1)
  - Division of Parole, 1977 (Box 1 (6-Division of Parole File), Folder 2)
  - Division of Parole, 1978-1979 (Box 1 (6-Division of Parole File), Folder 3)
  - Division of Parole, 1980-1983 (Box 1 (6-Division of Parole File), Folder 4)
  - "Good-Time" Development, 1978-1982 (Box 1 (6-Division of Parole File), Folder 5)
  - Parole Denial Statistics, 1980 (Box 1 (6-Division of Parole File), Folder 6)
- Department of Correctional Services Files, 1972-1983; 7; 0.67 cubic ft.
  The Division of Correctional Services is responsible for the care, custody, and rehabilitation of all offenders sentenced to its institutions. Included for the division of correctional services is a summary of appropriations and estimated expenditures for 1977, and a budget for 1980. Administrative bulletins can be found concerning such topics as work release, temporary release program violators, leave of absence and furlough 1972-1974. Also included are several Correctional services procedure directives concerning the inmate liaison committee, affirmative action, research studies and surveys, minimum provisions for health and morale, inmate group activities and organizations, and human rights complaints. Also found are inspection reports concerning fire and housing for the Elmira correctional center 1980-1982, inmate grievance mechanisms and case records 1975-1976.
  The correspondence of Richard Hongisto, acting commissioner for 1978, can be found along with a statement report concerning his plans and concerns for the criminal justice system which he addressed to the senate crime and correction committee 1979. Also included are legislative status sheets for 1979, and Prison security and staffing statistics for all prisons from Albion to Woodbourne for 1969-1976. From the office of program planning, evaluation and research, reports can be found concerning five year release programs 1975, the second felony offender sentencing act 1973-1974, delinquency and return rates 1976, and parole violators 1976. A rule book addressing inmate rules, penalties and outline of procedures for 1975 can also be found along with an employees handbook. Finally brochures on staying out of prison programs for 1982 are present, and temporary release program outlines, including regulations, reports and agreements for 1978-1981.
  Also, the series contains information on prison expansion debate, such as the Joint Legislative Committee Hearing, reports, tables, statistics, and surveys 1980-1982 and statistics on inmate population in New York State prisons.
  - Budget, 1977 (Box 1 (7-Department of Correctional Services Files), Folder 1)
  - Bulletins & Directives, 1972-1980 (Box 1 (7-Department of Correctional Services Files), Folder 2)
  - Commitment of Offense by Violent & Non-Violent Offense Groupings-Felony Class, 1981 (Box 1 (7-Department of Correctional Services Files), Folder 3)
  - Dialogues, 1977-1978 (Box 1 (7-Department of Correctional Services Files), Folder 4)
  - Five safety reports, 1980-1982 (Box 1 (7-Department of Correctional Services Files), Folder 5)
  - Grievance mechanism, 1975-1976 (Box 1 (7-Department of Correctional Services Files), Folder 6)
  - Hongisto, 1978-1979 (Box 1 (7-Department of Correctional Services Files), Folder 7)
  - Inmate Population Statistics, 1980-1982 (Box 1 (7-Department of Correctional Services Files), Folder 8)
  - Legislative Program, 1979 (Box 1 (7-Department of Correctional Services Files), Folder 9)
  - Pre-Release Center Brief, Undated (Box 1 (7-Department of Correctional Services Files), Folder 10)
  - Prison expansion, 1980-1982 (Box 2 (7-Department of Correctional Services Files), Folder 1)
  - Prison Security & Staffing Statistics, 1969-1978; 1980-1982 (Box 2 (7-Department of Correctional Services Files), Folder 2)
  - Probation, 1979-1980 (Box 2 (7-Department of Correctional Services Files), Folder 3)
  - Program Planning: Evaluation Research, 1975-1983 (Box 2 (7-Department of Correctional Services Files), Folder 4)
  - Rehabilitation vs. Cost Benefit, 1977 (Box 2 (7-Department of Correctional Services Files), Folder 5)
  - Reports, 1979-1981 (Box 2 (7-Department of Correctional Services Files), Folder 6)
  - Rule books, 1975-1977 (Box 2 (7-Department of Correctional Services Files), Folder 7)
  - "Stay' n Out" therapy program, 1982 (Box 2 (7-Department of Correctional Services Files), Folder 8)
  - Temporary release programs, 1978-1981 (Box 2 (7-Department of Correctional Services Files), Folder 9)
- "Good-Time" Attitude Survey, 1981; 8; 3.33 cubic ft.
  Contains the Coalition's Good-Time survey given to prison staff and inmates, computer print outs of survey coding, and miscellaneous notes of Peter Pollack concerning the survey. The Good-Time survey established prison staff and inmate attitudes toward the granting of early release or parole to inmates for good behavior. 642 completed surveys are also in the series but are being considered for destruction.
  - Survey Format, Undated (Box 1 (8-"Good-Time" Attitude Survey), Folder 1)
  - Computer Printouts, Undated (Box 1 (8-"Good-Time" Attitude Survey), Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous notes, Undated (Box 1 (8-"Good-Time" Attitude Survey), Folder 3)
  - Staff questionnaire forms 1-209, Undated (Box 2 (8-"Good-Time" Attitude Survey), Folder 1)
  - Staff questionnaire forms 210-393, Undated (Box 3 (8-"Good-Time" Attitude Survey), Folder 1)
  - Inmate questionnaire forms 501-642 (plus unmarked), Undated (Box 4 (8-"Good-Time" Attitude Survey), Folder 1)
- Issues File, 1971-1984; 9; 3.33 cubic ft.